今天我想谈谈 Go 语言
today I'd like to talk about Go which
它真的相当有趣
is interesting especially interesting
在这门课中
for us in this course because course Go
未来的 labs
is the language at the labs you're all
将使用 Go 语言来完成，所以今天我想
going to do the labs in and so I want to
花些精力关注
focus today particularly on some of the
在 labs 会用到的部分
machinery that sort of most useful in
特别是在
the labs and in most particular to
分布式程序中，嗯，首先
distributed programming um first of all
为什么在这门课里我们要使用 Go 语言？
you know it's worth asking why we use go
事实上，我们已经使用过
in this class in fact we could have used
其它风格的编程语言
any one of a number of other system
非常多，比如
style languages plenty languages like
Java, C#, 甚至是 Python
Java or C sharp or even Python that
这些语言提供了我们需要的工具
provide the kind of facilities we need
我们也在这门课用使用过 C++
and indeed we used to use C++ in this
并且它也能很好的得出满意的结果
class and it worked out fine it'll go
Go 也像其它编程语言一样
indeed like many other languages
给你打包了一些非常便利的功能（特性）
provides a bunch of features which are
供你使用
particularly convenient
尤其是在多线程、
that's good support for threads and
锁，以及线程间同步上，Go 都做的相当的棒！
locking and synchronization between
未来我们会大量使用这些特性
threads which we use a lot it is a
另外 RPC package(RPC 包)也相当的好用
convenient remote procedure call package
它听起来好像没什么大不了的
which doesn't sound like much but it
但是这在其它诸如 C++ 这样的语言中
actually turns out to be a significant
真的是个很大的包袱，用起来不尽人意
constraint from many languages like C++
比如说，你很难找到一个好用的
for example it's actually a bit hard to
RPC 包
find a convenient easy to use remote
当然了
procedure call package and of course we
在这门课里或是
use it all the time in this course or
程序中，并且在不同的机器上，我们会用它做比较
programs and different machines to talk
不像 C++, Go 是类型安全
to each other unlike C++ go is type safe
且内存安全的语言
and memory safe that is it's pretty hard
想要编写一个完美的程序真的太难了
to write a program that due to a bug
它总是或多或少存在和内存相关的 bug
scribbles over some random piece of
然后导致程序产生一些奇奇怪怪的事情
memory and then causes the program to do
然而，Go 的垃圾回收机制
mysterious things and that just
能尽可能的帮我们消灭大量类似的 bug
eliminates a big class of bugs similarly
这意味着
it's garbage collected which means you
你再也不用饱受 double free
never in danger of priam the same memory
或是释放正在被使用的内存的痛苦
twice or free memory that's still in use
还有一些不用的 vector
or something the garbage vector just
当它不被使用时，也应该要被释放掉
frees things when they stop being used
还有一些看起来不太明显的问题
and one thing it's maybe not obvious
直到你接触
until you played around with just this
这样的程序之前
kind of programming before but the
多线程协同，垃圾回收
combination of threads and garbage
也是相当重要的事情之一
collection is particularly important one
在非垃圾回收型语言中
of the things that goes wrong in a non
这些都很容易出错，比如 C++
garbage collected language like C++ if
如果你使用它(C++)编写多线程程序
you use threads is that it's always a
它总会出现一些让人迷惑的的问题
bit of a puzzle and requires a bunch of
这要求你需要一大本草稿本帮助你去理解
bookkeeping to figure out when the last
什么时候最后一个线程
thread
不在使用共享对象
that's using a shared object has
因为只有
finished using that object because only
在这个时候，你才能释放对象
then can you free the object and so you end
所以最终你会写很多代码
up writing quite a bit of code just like
就像许多程序员会
many of the programmer writes about a
自己动手写一堆代码那样
bunch of code manually. you know do
你知道可以实现类似引用计数这样的功能
reference counting or something in order
来解决它，你也知道
to figure out you know when the last
当最后一个使用对象的线程结束时（需要释放它）
thread stopped using an object and
那真是相当的痛苦
that's just a pain and that problem
如果有垃圾回收，这些问题都将不复存在
completely goes away if you use garbage
比如在 Go 语言中
collection like we have in go
最后一点，这门语言比 C++ 要简单的多。
and finally the language is simple much
使用 C++ 的麻烦的问题之一，比如
simpler than C++ one of the problems
你可能只是一个拼写错误
with using C++ is that often if you made
它就可能导致编译器
an error you know maybe even just a typo
报出非常复杂的错误信息
the the error message you get back from
在 C++ 里
the compiler is so complicated that in
尝试去理解这些
C++ it's usually not worth trying to
错误信息不太值得了
figure out what the error message meant
我觉得更好、更快的方法
and I find it's always just much quicker
就是去看看出错的那一行代码
to go look at the line number and try to
尝试去猜测它到底是什么错误
guess what the error must have been
因为这门语言真是太
because the language is far too
复杂了
complicated
然而 Go，你懂的，
whereas go is you know probably doesn't
它没有许多让人热衷的特性
have a lot of people's favorite features
相对而言它是一门“直接了当”
but it's relatively straightforward
的语言。Okay, 所以现在你们
language okay so at this point you're
都应该看看 Go 语言教程
both on the tutorial if you're looking
如果你正在纠结关于这门语言，你下一步应该学习什么的时候
for sort of you know what to look at
有一个好东西你可以看看
next to learn about the language a good
名为《Effective Go》
place to look is the document titled
你可以通过
effective go which you know you can find
互联网搜索到这本书
by searching the web
好吧，现在我们谈谈多线程
all right the first thing I want to talk about is threads
在这门课里
the reason why we care a lot about
为什么要关注多线程？
threads in this course is that threads
线程将是在这门课中
are the sort of main tool we're going to
实现并发的重要工具
be using to manage concurrency in
在分布式程序中
programs and concurrency is a particular
并发相当有意思
interest in distributed programming
比较常见的情况是
because it's often the case that one
一个程序需要同时
program actually needs to talk to a
和多台计算机通信
bunch of other computers you know client
客户端可能会同时和多台服务器通信
may talk to many servers or a server may
一台服务器可能会同时响应
be serving requests at the same time on
来自不同客户端的多条请求
behalf of many different clients and so
我们需要一种方式来解释，，，噢，你知道我是
we need a way to say oh you know I'm my
我的程序同时有 7 个不同的事情在进行
program really has seven different
因为它正和 7 个不同
things going on because it's talking to
客户端在通信
seven different clients and I want a
我想要一种简单的方式
simple way to allow it to do these seven
实现它能同时做 7 件不同的事情
different things you know without too
我不需要做太复杂的编程
much complex programming I mean sort of
线程就能很好的解决它
thrust threads are the answer so these
在 Go 的文档中，
are the things that the go documentation
它把线程称为 goroutine
calls go routines which I call threads
goroutine 真的很像
the go routines are really this same
大家所说的线程
as what everybody else calls threads
你可以这样来思考线程
so the way to think of threads is
你有一个程序
that you have a program，one program
有一个地址空间，让我来画个小盒子
and one address space I'm gonna draw a
来表示地址空间
box to sort of denote an address space
在这个地址空间里
and within that address space in a
串行执行的程序是没有多个线程的
serial program without threads you just
你只有一个线程
have one thread of execution executing
它在这个地址空间中执行代码
code in that address space one program
它只有一个程序计数器，只有一套寄存器，一个（运行时）栈
counter one set of registers one stack
这些东西就能描述
that are sort of describing the current
当前的执行状态
state of the execution
在一个多线程程序中，比方说 Go 程序
in a threaded program like a go program you could have
你可以拥有多个线程，
multiple threads and you know I got raw
我来画些弯弯的线条来表示它
it as multiple squiggly lines and when
每条线之间都是分开的
each line represents really is a
特别是，
separate if the especially if the
如果这些线程同时执行
threads are executing at the same time
那它们就分别有一个属于自己的程序计数器
but a separate program counter a
一套寄存器和一个栈
separate set of registers and a separate
是的，每个线程都有自己的一套东西
stack for each of the threads so that
自己的一套线程控制
they can have a sort of their own thread
他们可以在程序中不同的部分
of control and be executing each thread
执行每个线程
in a different part of the program and
有一个不太让人注意的细节
so hidden here is that for every stack
每一个独立的线程都有一个栈
there's a seprate thread there's a
这些栈都在执行
stack that it's executing on
这些栈都在程序中的同一个地址空间里
the stacks are actually in in the one address space
所以，即使
of the program so even though each stack
每个线程都有它自己的栈
each thread has its own stack
严格来讲他们都在同一地址空间中
technically the they're all in the same
如果知道正确的地址的话
address space and different threads
不同的线程总会关联到自己的栈上
could refer to each other stacks if they
knew the right addresses
尽管你通常不会这么干
although you typically don't do that
在 Go 中，即便在只有 main 函数的程序中
and in go, when you even the main program you know when
当你首次启动程序时
you first start up the program and it
它会在 main 函数中运行
runs in main that's also it's just a go
它就是一个 goroutine，然后做完所有的事情
routine and can do all the things that goroutine can do
好啦
all right so as I
我想说的最重要的原因
mentioned one of the big reasons is
就是允许程序中不同的部分
to allow different parts of the program to
都能独立的
sort of be in its own point in a
执行不同的动作
different activity so I usually refer to
我常常说 IO 并发是出于历史原因
that as IO concurrency for historical
称之为 IO 并发
reasons and the reason I call it IO
是因为在过去这个概念
concurrency is that in the old days
第一次被提出的时候是这样的：
where this first came up is that
你可能有一个线程
oh you might have one thread that's waiting to
正在等待从磁盘上读数据
read from the disk and while it's waiting to
当它在等待的时候，你又想要
reach from the disk you'd like to have a
另一个线程，可能用来做计算或是
second thread that maybe can compute or
从某个磁盘的地方读取数据
read somewhere else in the disk or send
或是向网络发送一条消息并等待回复
a message in the network and wait for reply
所以 IO 并发
and so I/O concurrency is one of
也是你使用多线程的地方之一
the things that threads by you for us it
比如说
would usually mean I can I/O concurrency
我们有一个程序
we usually mean I can have one program
已经启动并且通过 RPC
that has launched, remote procedure
请求网络上不同的服务器
calls requests to different servers on
然后同时在等待多个回复
the network and is waiting for many replies at the same time
这就是我们要解决的问题
that's how it'll come up for us
具体做法是
and you know the way you would do that with threads is
你会为每个 RPC 调用创建一个线程
that you would create one thread for each of the remote procedure calls that
每个线程
you wanted to launch that thread would
都会通过 RPC 发送 request 消息
have code that you know sent the remote procedure call request message and sort
然后在这个位置等待
of waited at this point in the thread
当响应回复时
and then finally when the reply came
这个线程将会继续执行
back the thread would continue executing
使用多线程
and using threads allows us to have
可以让我们同时发起多个网络请求
multiple threads that all launch requests into the network at the same time
所有线程都会等待回复
they all wait or they don't have to
也不是非得在同一时间去发请求
do it at the same time they can you know
只要它愿意，这些线程总可以做不同的事情
execute the different parts of this whenever they feel like it
不同 IO 并发活动可能会有互相重叠的部分
so that's i/o concurrency sort of overlapping of the progress of different activities
也允许一个活动正在等待，另一个活动可以继续执行
and allowing while one activity is waiting, other activities can proceed
使用多线程的另一个最重要原原因是多核并行
another big reason to use threads is multi-core parallelism
我就写并行化吧
which I'll just call parallelism
我们想通过线程来达到并行化的目的
and here the thing where we'd be trying to achieve with threads
并行化就是如果你有个多核机器
is if you have a multi-core
我确定你们每个人都能用你的笔记本做到
machine like I'm sure all of you do in
如果你有一个计算繁重的工作
your laptops if you have a sort of
它需要消耗许多 CPU 时钟
compute heavy job that needs a lot of
这不是太好
CPU cycles wouldn't it be nice if you
假设你的程序
could have one program that could use
能使用机器上所有的 CPU 核
CPU cycles on all of the cores of the
比方说它是用 Go 写的多线程程序
machine and indeed if you write a multi-threaded go
你启动了多个 goroutine
if you launch multiple go routines and go and they do something
这些 goroutine 执行一些计算密集型的任务
computer intensive like sit there in a
比如一直在那执行一个循环，计算 pi（圆周率)的值
loop and you know compute digits of pi
直到达到机器上 cpu 核的极限
or something then up to the limit of the number of cores in the physical machine
你的线程将会真正的以并行的方式运行
your threads will run truly in parallel
如果你启动 2 个线程代替 1 个线程
and if you launch you know two threads
你就能获得 2 倍的性能
instead of one you'll get twice as many
就能使用 2 倍数量的 CPU 核时钟
you'll be able to use twice as many CPU cycles per second
对部分人来说这真的太重要了
so this is very
但是在这门课里
important to some people it's not a big
这其实没什么大不了的
deal on this course
我们并不会把多过精力
be... it's rare that we'll sort of think
放在这一类并行化上
specifically about this kind of parallelism
在现实世界中
in the real world though of
我们开发像服务器这样的程序
building things like servers to form
来组成分布式系统的一部分
parts of the distributed systems it can
有时让服务器
sometimes be extremely important to be
能使用多线程
able to have the server be able to run
能使用多核还是非常重要的
threads and harness the CPU power of a
因为往往客户端
lot of cores just because the load from
带给服务器的负载非常高
clients can often be pretty high
okay, 所以并行化是第二个原因
okay so parallelism is a second reason
那么为什么咱们会在分布式系统中
why threads are quite a bit interested in
如此关注多线程呢
distributed systems and a third reason
第三个原因，但也可能不那么重要
which is maybe a little bit less
就是有时候
important is there's some there's times
你只是想在后台做一些事情
when you really just want to be able to do something in the background
比如你就想周期性的去执行它
or you know there's just something you need to do periodically
但你又不愿意在主线程
and you don't want to have to sort of in the main part of your
插入一些检查
program sort of insert checks to say
比如我要做的那个动作
well should I be doing this things that
它应该每秒发生一次
should happen every second or so you
就像你生火一样
just like to be able to fire something
每秒都能做
up that every second does whatever the
不管周期性执行做什么事情
periodic thing is
都有一些原因
so there's some convenience reasons
这里有个例子
and an example which will come up for you
也是经常会遇到的情况
is it's often the case
比如有一个 master 服务就需要周期性的检查它的 worker 服务
that some you know a master server may want to check periodically whether
是否一直存活
its workers are still alive because one
因为这些 worker 之一宕机的话
of them is died you know you want to
就需要把工作扔到另一台机器上去执行
launch that work on another machine like
就像 MapReduce 那样
MapReduce might do that and one way to
你可以每秒、每分钟
arrange sort of oh do this check every
通过发送一条“你还活着吗？”这样的消息到 worker 服务上
second every minute you know send a message to the worker are you alive is
你能启动一个 goroutine
to fire off a go routine that just sits
然后执行一个死循环，sleep 1 秒后
in a loop that sleeps for a second and
然后做需要周期执行的动作
then does the periodic thing and then
然后又 sleep 1 秒
sleeps for a second again and so in the
在后面的 lab 里，你最后将会创建这样的线程
labs you'll end up firing off these kind of threads quite a bit
（提问...猜测是开启 goroutine 开销的问题）
yes is the
这个开销是值得的，是的，这个开销
overhead worth it yes the overhead is
真的非常少
really pretty small for this stuff I
这依赖于你创建多少线程
mean you know it depends on how many you
但是如果你创建了 100 万个线程
create a million threads that he sit in
每个线程中执行循环，循环只 sleep 1 毫秒
a loop waiting for a millisecond and
然后发送网络消息
then send a network message that's
这可能会给你的机器带来巨大的负载
probably a huge load on your machine but
如果你就创建了 10 个线程的话
if you create you know ten threads that
sleep 1 秒，然后做一点点工作
sleep for a second and do a little bit
这真的没什么大不了的
of work it's probably not a big deal at all
我保证这会节约你很多时间
and it's I guarantee you the programmer time you
你不用把各种不同的
save by not having the sort of much
功能搞到一起
together they're different different
放在一行代码里
activities into one line of code it's
它只会消耗一点点 CPU
it's worth the small amount of CPU cost almost always
如果很不幸
still you know you will if
你在 Labs 发现
you're unlucky you'll discover in the
有些循环 sleep 的时间不够长
labs that some loop of yours is not
或者是创建了大量的 goroutine
sleeping long enough or are you fired
也从未让他们退出
off a bunch of these and never made them
这样 goroutine 就会越来越多
exit for example and they just
甚至是你做的更过火
accumulate so you can push it too far
okay，所以这些原因
okay so these are the reasons that the
是人们喜欢线程的主要原因
main reasons that people like threads a
也是我们在这门课里使用多线程的原因
lot and that will use threads in this
关于线程大家还有什么问题吗？
class any other questions about threads
（提问：...）通过异步编程
in general by asynchronous program you
你的意思是通过单线程
mean like a single thread of control
来追踪不同活动的状态是吗？
that keeps state about many different
yeah，这真的是个好问题
activities yeah so this is a good question actually
如果不使用多线程会怎样？
there is you know what would happen if we didn't have threads
可能因为某些原因我们不想使用线程
or we'd for some reason we didn't want
那么我们如何写程序？
to use threads like how would we be able to write a program
你知道服务器
that could you know a server
能够同时与不同客户端通信
that could talk to many different clients at the same time
或是客户端能同时与多个服务器通信
or a client that could talk to many servers right
这时候应该使用什么样的工具？
what what tools could be used and it
事实上还有另一种方式
turns out there is sort of another line
另一种主要风格
of another kind of another major style
这种组织程序的方式称为异步编程
of how do you structure these programs called you call the asynchronous program
也称为事件驱动编程
I might call it event-driven programming
你可以使用事件驱动编程
so sort of or you could use event-driven
事件驱动编程的一般结构
programming and the the general structure of an event-driven program is
通常它有一个线程
usually that it has a single thread and
同时有一个循环
a single loop and what that loop does is
这个循环等待输入
sits there and waits for any input or
或者是其它任何事件
sort of any event that might trigger
这些事件能触发程序继续进行
processing so an event might be the
事件可能是一个来自客户端的请求
arrival of a request from a client or a
可能是定时器到期，如果你在编写
timer going off or if you're building a
windows 系统程序
Windows System, many Windows
你电脑上的许多 windows 系统程序
systems on your laptops I've driven
都是通过事件驱动的风格来编写的
written an event-driven style where what
它们等待的东西是像键盘击键
they're waiting for is like key clicks
或者是鼠标移动这样的事件
or Mouse move
因此你可能会有一个单一的
or something so you might have a single
只有一个控制线程的程序
an event-driven programing of a
这个线程有一个循环一直等待输入
single thread of control sits a loop
无论何时有输入进来
waits for input and whenever it gets an
比如收到报文，它能够找出来
input like a packet it figures out oh
是哪个客户端发送的这个报文
you know which client did this packet
它有一张表格
come from and then it'll have a table of
记录这个客户端到底处于什么样的活动状态
sort of what the state is of whatever activity its managing for that client
比如说，oh 上帝，
and it'll say oh gosh I was in the
我现在处于“读”某个文件的状态
middle of reading such-and-such a file
那么它就会要求我去读下一个数据块
you know now it's asked me to read the
然后我就会去读取下一个数据块然后返回
next block I'll go and be the next block
使用线程的话
and return it and threads are generally
通常会变的更加方便
more convenient because they allow you
因为线程能让你更容易把把程序写的连贯有序
to really you know it's much easier to write sequential
你就一溜写下来几行代码
just like straight lines of control code that does you know
计算，然后发送消息，然后等待响应
computes sends a message waits for
这比在只有一个线程里
response whatever it's much easier to write that kind of code in a thread than
把一个活动给分割成一块一块的办法要容易多了
it is to chop up whatever the activity is into a bunch of little pieces that
在事件驱动循环里
can sort of be activated one at a time
你一次只能执行一个活动
by one of these event-driven loops
这种编程模式的问题在于
that said they are and so one problem with
它实现起来有点痛苦
the scheme is that it's it's a little bit of a pain to program
另一个潜在的缺陷
another potential defect is that while you get
当你用这种方法获取了 IO 并发后
io concurrency from this approach you
你就没法利用 CPU 的并行化机制
don't get CPU parallelism so if you're
所以当你写一个负载很高的服务
writing a busy server that would really
你得相当设法把一台大型机器的 32 核都用上
like to keep you know 32 cores busy on a big server machine
使用一个单一循环的话，你知道，它相当的不自然
you know a single loop is you know it's it's not a very
也很难获得多核的性能
natural way to harness more than one core
另一方面，
on the other hand the overheads of
冒这样的风险编程
adventure programming are generally
通常换来的性能提升相比多线和来说并不会太多
quite a bit less than threads you know
而且线程相对来说也很廉价
threads are pretty cheap but each one of
但是每个线程都有一个栈
these threads is sitting on a stack you
栈通常是 1kb 或数千字节
know stack is a kilobyte or a kilobytes
如果你有 20 个线程
or something you know if you have 20 of
这些消耗根本不用在意
these threads who cares if you have a
但是你若有 100 万个线程
million of these threads then it's
那它就会消耗大量的内存
starting to be a huge amount of memory
另外，线程调度
and you know maybe the scheduling
就是决定下一步选择哪个线程运行
bookkeeping for deciding what the thread to run next might also start you know
有一个调度列表，上面记录了 1000 个线程
you now have list scheduling lists with a thousand threads in them
线程的执行将付出相当昂贵的代码
the threads can start to get quite expensive so if
所以，当你只有一个服务器的时候
you are in a position where you need to
你的服务器需要为 100 万个客户端提供服务
have a single server that serves you know a million clients
你需要为这 100 万个客户端记录一些状态
and has to sort of keep a little bit of state for each of a million clients
这个代码还是挺高的
this could be expensive
花点时间的话，应该容易写一个……你知道
and it's easier to write a very you know at some expense in programmer time
使用事件驱动编程的话
it's easier to write a really stripped-down
更容易写一个简单的而又五脏俱全高性能的服务
efficient low overhead service in event-driven programming
只是要花点时间
just a lot more work
你是问我 JavaScript 吗？
are you asking my JavaScript I
你这个问题我也不会
don't know the question is whether
JavaScript 有没有利用多核这个……
JavaScript has multiple cores executing
有人知道吗? 这得取决于具体实现
your does anybody know depends on the implementation
yeah，不过我确实不太清楚这个
yeah so I don't know
有个很自然的想法
I mean it's a natural thought though even
即使是在 Go 中
in you know even in Go you might well
假设你知道你的机器有 8 个核
want to have if you knew your machine
你想写一个世界上最高效的 server
had eight cores if you wanted to write
你可能就会启动 8 个线程
the world's most efficient whatever server you could fire up eight threads
每个线程上运行一个精简的事件驱动循环
and on each of the threads run sort of stripped-down event-driven loop
一个循环一个核
just you know sort of one event loop per core and
对于 IO 并发来说，这是一种获得并行化的方式
that you know that would be a way to get both parallelism and to the I/O concurrency concurrency
(提问)
yes
okay，所以你想问多线程与多进程的区别是什么对吧
okay so the question is what's the difference between threads and processes
通常，对于类 UNIX 系统的机器来说
so usually on a like a UNIX machine a
一个进程就是一个单独运行的程序
process is a single program that you're
只有一个地址空间
running and a sort of single address
一大片可供进程使用的内存
space a single bunch of memory for the
在这个进程里你可能同时会有好多个线程
process and inside a process you might have multiple threads
当你准备好一个 go 程序并运行
and when you ready a go program and you run the go program
将会创建一个 unix 进程和一块内存区
running the go program creates one unix process and one sort of memory area
当你的 Go 进程创建 goroutine 时
and then when your go process creates go
它们实际上都是在同一个进程里的
routines those are so sitting inside that one process
我不太确定真实的答案是不是这样
so I'm not sure that's really an answer but just historically
但历史上，操作系统都提供了像这样的大盒子
the operating systems have provided like
它就是个进程
this big box is the process that's
实际上这也取决于操作系统的实现
implemented by the operating system and
确实有个别人或一些操作系统
the individual and some of the operating
并不关心你的进程内部到底发生了什么事情
system does not care what happens inside
也不关心你使用什么语言
your process what language you use none
不关心操作系统内部的业务逻辑
of the operating systems business but
在进程内部能运行多个线程就行了
inside that process you can run lots of
好，如果在你的机器上运行了不止一个进程
threads now you know if you run more than one process in your machine you know you run more than one program
比如一个编辑器或是编译器
like an editor or compiler
操作系统需要让它们彼此分开
the operating system keep quite separate
你的编译器和你的编译器
right you're your editor and your compiler each have
都有自己的内存空间
memory but it's not the same memory that
他们之间无法看到彼此的内存
are not allowed to look at each other
不同的进程之间不会有交集
memory there's not much interaction between different processes so
你的编译器可能有多个线程
your edditor may have threads and your
你的编译器也可能有多个线程
compiler may have threads but they're
但是他们都处于各自的世界
just in different worlds so within any
但是在同一个进程中，线程与线程之间可以共享内存
one program the threads can share memory
可以使用 channel(Go语言中的概念) 进行同步
and can synchronize with channels and
也可以使用 mutex 等
use mutexes etc. but between
但进程之间是没有交集的
processes there's just no no interaction
这类软件的传统结构就是这样
that's just a traditional structure of these this kind of software
(提问)
yeah
问题：当上下文切换时，是所有线程都在切换吗？
so the question is when a context switch happens does it happened for all threads
okay，我们想象一下
okay so let's let's imagine you have a
你只有一个单核机器
single core machine that's really only
这意味着在同一个时刻你只能做一件事情
running and as just doing one thing at a
你这样想
time maybe the right way to think about
你打算在你的机器上运行多进程
it is that you're going to be you're running multiple processes on your machine
操作系统把 CPU 时间片
the operating system will give
反复的分配给这两个程序
the CPU sort of time slicing back and forth between these two programs
当硬件时钟到期时
so when the hardware timer ticks and the
操作系统就判断是时候把 CPU 从当前正在运行的进程剥夺
operating systems decides it's time to take away the CPU from the currently running process
然后把 CPU 分配给另一个进程
and give it to another
这件事件是在进程级别上做的
process that's done at a process level
这有点复杂，好
it's complicated all right let me let me
让我们重新再思考这个问题
let me restart this these the threads
我们使用的线程最终是由是操作系统线程所提供的
that we use are based on threads that are provided by the operating system in the end
当操作系统上下文切换时
and when the operating system's
就是不同的线程之间产生切换时
context switches its switching between
操作系统是知道这一切的
the threads that it knows about so in a
所以操作系统可能会清楚
situation like this the operating system
这儿有两个线程在这个进程中，有三个线程在那个进程
might know that there are two threads here in this process and three threads in this process
当时钟到期时
and when the timer ticks
操作系统会基于一些调度算法选择一个不同的线程来运行
the operating system will based on some scheduling algorithm pick a different thread thread to run
在这个进程中的线程和另一进程中的线程可能是不同的
it might be a different thread in this process or one of the threads in this process
另外，Go 会聪明复用一个操作系统线程
in addition go cleverly multiplex as
在上面运行尽可能多的 goroutine 以节省开支
many go routines on top of single operating system threads to reduce overhead
所以这可能需要两个阶段去调度
so it's really probably a two
首先操作系统选择一个线程去运行
stages of scheduling the operating system picks which big thread to run
然后在这个进程中，Go 会再去选择哪个 goroutine 去运行
and then within that process go may have a choice of go routines to run
好啦，线程真的很方便
all right okay so threads are convenient
大多数时候，使用它就能让你在每个线程中写出非常普通、连贯的代码
because a lot of times they allow you to write the code for each thread just as if it were a pretty ordinary sequential program
然而，事实上写多线程程序是有些挑战的
however there are in fact some challenges with writing threaded code
其中一个是共享数据
one is what to do about shared data one
关于线程模型，牛逼的地方在于
of the really cool things about the
这些线程共享地址空间，共享内存
threading model is that these threads share the same address space they share memory
如果某个线程在内存中创建了一个对象
if one thread creates an object
在其它线程中你也能使用它
in memory you can let other threads use
你可以创建个数组或是别的什么东西
it right you can have a array or
所有不同的线程都能读写
something that all the different threads are reading and writing and that
这就存在一些临界情况
sometimes critical right if you you know
如果你你持有一些你关注的状态
if you're keeping some interesting state
可能你会缓存一些数据
you know maybe you have a cache of
你的 server，你的缓存，你的内存
things that your server your cache and
当其中一个线程正处理一个客户端的请求的时候
memory when a thread is handling a
首先它会先查一下缓存中的数据
client request it's gonna first look in
但是这个共享缓存，每个线程都能读
that cache but the shared cache and each
当线程里有新的信息时，线程可能会向缓存里写入数据进行更新
thread reads it and the threads may write the cache to update it when they have new information to stick in the cache
所以这真的很厉害
so it's really cool you can share
你可以共享内存
that memory but it turns out that it's
但是事实也表明这也非常容易出现 bug
very very easy to get bugs if you're not
如果你不关心多线程之间共享内存的话
careful and you're sharing memory between threads
有个经典的例子
so a totally classic example is you know supposing your
假设你有一个全局变量 N
thread so you have a global variable N
在不同的线程之间共享
and that's shared among the different
其中一个线程只是对 N 做自增
threads and a thread just wants to
这可能就是造成 bug 的原因
increment n right but itself this is likely to be an invitation to bugs right
如果你不做一些特殊处理的话
if you don't do anything special around this code
为什么？
and the reason is that you
无论何时你在多线程中读写共享数据
know whenever you write code in a thread that you you know is accessing reading or writing data that's shared with other
总是存在一种可能性
threads you know there's always the
你得牢记
possibility and you got to keep in mind
在同一时刻，总有其它的线程可能也正在查看，或是修改这个共享数据
that some other thread may be looking at the data or modifying the data at the same time
所以这里有个很明显的问题
so the obvious problem with
看这里，线程 1 正在执行
this is that maybe thread 1 is executing this code and thread 2 is actually
但是另一个不同的线程 2 也在执行相同的代码
in the same function in a different thread executing the very same code
记得刚我说 N 它是一个全局变量
right and remember I'm imagining the N is a global
所以这里我们说的这个 N 都是同一个 N
variable so they're talking about the
这里再总结一下
same n so what this boils down to you
实际上机器运行的并不是这样的代码
know you're not actually running this
而是由编译器吐出来的机器码
code you're running machine code the compiler produced and
机器码长啥样呢
what that machine code does is it you
首先把 X 载入到一个寄存器里
know it loads X into a register
然后把这个寄存器的加 1
you know adds one to the register and
接着再把寄存器的值保存到 X
then stores that register into X with
这里 X 是某个位置的内存地址
where X is a address of some location
所以你可以指望所有的线程
and ran so you know you can count on both of the threads
都在执行这行代码
they're both executing this line of code
他们都会执行 load x 到寄存器
you know they both load the variable X
x 从 0 开始有效
into a register an effect starts out at 0
这意味着，所有线程都把 0 读入寄存器
that means they both load at 0
然后他们都给寄存器加 1
they both increment that register so
这样所有线程各有自的寄存器的值是 1
they get one and they both store one
最后再把寄存器的值 1 重新保存到内存里
back to memory and now two threads of
现在，这两个线程对 N 做自增后，结果都是 1
incremented n and the resulting value is 1
谁知道程序员心里想的啥呢
which well who knows what the
可能他就是这么想
programmer intended maybe that's what
但是碰巧这样写并不正确
the programmer wanted but chances are
碰巧程序想要的结果不是 1
not right chances are the programmer wanted to not 1
(提问...) 有一些指令是原子的
no, some some instructions
这个问题不错
are atomic so the question is a very
这些独立的指令是不是原子的
good question which it's whether individual instructions are atomic
答案是有些是，有些不是
so the answer is some are and some aren't
对于 32 位的 store 指令它极有可能是原子的
so a store a 32-bit store is likely the extremely likely to be atomic
从某种意义上来说，如果有两个处理器同时在相同的内存地址上执行 store 一个 32 位值
in the sense that if 2 processors store at the same time to the same memory address 32-bit values
最终要么是其中一个处理器上的 32 位值，要么是另一个处理器上的 32 位值
well you'll end up with is either the 32 bits from one processor or the 32 bits from the other processor
而不是一个混合的值
but not a mixture
其它尺寸大小的未必就这么清晰，
other sizes it's not so clear like one byte stores it depends on
比如一个字节的存储这依赖于你所使用的 CPU
the CPU you using because a one byte
因为 1 字节的存储几乎和 32 字节的 load 差不多
store is really almost certainly a 32
就是 8 bit 的修改，和一个 32 字节的存储
byte load and then a modification of 8 bits and a 32 byte store
这依赖于处理器和更复杂的指令
but it depends on the processor and more complicated instructions
比如微处理器上的自增指令
like increment your microprocessor may well have an increment instruction
它能直接给内存上某个地址的值加 1
that can directly increment some memory location like
未必就是原子的
pretty unlikely to be atomic although
尽管这些指令存在原子版本的
there's atomic versions of some of these instructions
好，咱们继续。所以这是一个非常经典的错误
so there's no. any way all right so this is this is a just classic danger
通常我们叫他“竞争”(注：后面不译，直接使用 race)，后面我打算会多次提起它
and it's usually called a race I'm gonna come up a lot
因为你将会做大量的多线程编程
cause you're gonna do a lot of
且存在共享状态
threaded programming with shared state
这里 race 这个词，我认为来源于电子电路中的一类古老的 bug
race I think refers to as some ancient class of bugs involving electronic circuits
但是对我们来说，称为 race 是因为如果一个 CPU 已经开始执行这段代码
but for us that you know the reason why it's called a race is because if one of the CPUs have started
另一些线程正在结束这段代码
executing this code and the other one the others thread is sort of getting close to this code
这就是 race
it's sort of a race
第一个处理器能够
as to whether the first processor can
在第二个处理器开始执行 load 前执行 store
finish and get to the store before the second processor start status execute the load
如果第一个处理器的 store
if the first processor actually
确实是在第二个处理器 load 之前
manages it to do the store before the second processor gets to the load then
那么第二个处理器就能看到第一个处理器存储的值
the second processor will see the stored
第二个处理器将 load 值 1，然后再加 1，再把 2 存入
value and the second processor will load one and add one to it in store two
好了，你可以通过上面这种方式理解这个术语
that's how you can justify this terminology
okay, 解决这个问题的方式很简单
okay and so the way you solve this certainly something this simple
加个锁就行了
is you insert locks
你知道，作为一个程序员
you know you as a programmer you have
你心中应该有一些办法如何给数据加锁
some strategy in mind for locking the
只有在持有锁的时候，这个共享数据才能被使用
data you can say well you know this piece of shared data can only be used when such-and-such a lock is held and
到后面你就会明白
you'll see this and you may have used
在后面的教程里你可能就会用到
this in the tutorial the go calls locks
Go 调用 lock 来锁住 mutex，你能看到 mu.Lock()
mutexes so what you'll see is a mu dot lock
加在这一段使用共享数据的代码前面
before a sequence of code that uses
然后在结束的地方调用  mu.Unlock()
shared data and you unlock afterwards
无论哪个线程执行到这里
and then whichever two threads execute
只有足够幸运的那个线程才能第一个抢到锁
this one that everyone is lucky enough to get the lock first
然后执行所有这些代码
gets to do all this stuff
在结束之前，另一个线程都不能继续
and finish before the other one is allowed to proceed
你可以考虑把这些在锁中间的代码封装起来
and so you can think of wrapping a some code in a lock
就像这一堆东西
as making a bunch of you know remember
记住，尽管这里只有一行代码
this even though it's one line it's
实际上这里也有 3 条不同的指令
really three distinct operations you can
对于必须加锁的人来说，
think of a lock as causing this sort of multi-step code sequence to be atomic
你可以认为锁能把这一连串的代码变成一个原子操作
with respect to other people who have to lock
(提问)
yes
你是……胆子小吗，能不能再说一遍？
should you sissy can you repeat the question
oh，这个问题很棒
oh that's a great question the question
Go 怎么知道我们正锁住哪些变量？
was how does go know which variable
在这里
we're locking right here of course is
就只有一个变量
only one variable but maybe we're locking
但是也可能我们会锁住等于 x + y 的值
an equals x plus y really threes few
实际上三个不同变量
different variables and the answer is
所以答案是 go 并不知道
that go has no idea it's not there's no
他们一点关联都没有
association at all
在这个锁里的任何位置
anywhere between this lock so this new
所以，这里新的东西是这个变量(mu)
thing is a variable which is a tight
它是个 mutex，
mutex there's just there's no
在 lock 和任何变量之间
association in the language between the
他们并没有什么关联
lock and any variables the associations
在程序员脑袋中
in the programmers head so as a
你只需要说：
programmer you need to say oh here's a
oh, 这里有一堆共享数据
bunch of shared data and any time you
在任意时刻，你修改其中任意一个
modify any of it you know here's a
有些复杂的数据结构
complex data structure say a tree or an
比如是树或是可扩展的 hash 表或是别的什么
expandable hash table or something
任何时候你若打算修改它
anytime you're going to modify it and of
当然，树是有许多对象组合而成的
course a tree is composed many many
任何时候，你打算修改任何
objects anytime you got to modify
和这个数据结构关联的东西
anything that's associated with this
你都得先拿到这样的锁
data structure you have to hold such and
当然，包含许多对象
such a lock. and of course, many
以及对象的集合的修改
objects and the set of objects changes
因为你可能会分配一个新的树节点
because you might allocate new tree
但是程序员必须想出一个策略
nodes but it's really the programmer who
保证在同一时刻
sort of works out a strategy for
数据结构只在一个核上被使用
ensuring that the data structure is used
所以
by only one core at a time and so it
需要创建一个甚至是多个锁
creates the one or maybe more locks and
有许多许多加锁的方案
there's many many locking strategies you
应用到树上
could apply to a tree you can imagine a
你可以想象一棵树上所有的树节点只有一个锁
tree with a lock for every tree node the
程序员可以制定一些策略来分配锁
programmer works out the strategy
在脑子里记住数据之间关系
allocates the locks and keeps in the programmers head the relationship to the data
但是对 Go 来说
but go for go it's this is this
这里的这个锁其实非常简单
lock it's just like a very simple thing
它是一个锁对象
there's a lock object the first thread
第一个线程调用 lock 方法拿到锁
that calls lock gets the lock other
其它所有线程等待直接 unlock 被执行
threads have to wait until unlocks
所有这些事情 Go 都清楚
and that's all go knows
(提问)
yeah
不用给一个对象中
does it not lock all variables that are
所有变量都加上锁吗？
part of the object go doesn't know
Go 不知道变量和锁之间是什么关系
anything about the relationship between
当你请求锁的时候
variables and locks so when you acquire
当你的代码调用 lock 方法时
that lock when you have code that calls
它在做什么
lock exactly what it is doing it is
它就是想拿到这个锁，这就是它的作用
acquiring this lock and that's all this
其它任何人想尝试获得锁对象
does and anybody else who tries to lock
所以在某个地方
objects so somewhere else who would have
需要声明一个 mutex mu;
declared you know mutex mu all right
这个 mu 指向了某些特别的 lock 对象
and this mu refers to some particular
有许多（听不懂。。。）
lock object and there are many many
所有这些动作都是获取这把锁
locks right all this does is acquires
其它任何人想获得它
this lock and anybody else who wants to
都需要等待，直到 unlock 这把锁
acquire it has to wait until we unlock
作为程序员，我们使用锁保护保护什么
this lock that's totally up to us as
就是所有我们要做的事情
programmers what we were protecting with
(提问) 所以问题是
that lock so the question is is it
让锁私有会不会好些
better to have the lock be a private the
数据结构的私有数据
private business of the data structure
我们假设有个城市的分区图
like supposing it a zoning map yeah and
你可能希望，尽管这不是真的
you know you would hope although it's
地图内部需要有一把锁来保护它
not true that map internally would have
这是个合理的策略
a lock protecting it and that's a reasonable strategy
有了这些会怎样？
would be to have them, I mean what would be to have them if you
如果你定义了一个
define a data structure that needs to be
需要加锁使用的数据结构
locked to have the lock be sort of
这个锁是内部私有的
interior that have each of the data
数据结构的每个方法都有责任
structures methods be responsible for
请求这把锁
acquiring that lock and the user the
用户，数据结构可能永远都不知道有这把锁的存在
data structure may never know that
这个相当合理
that's pretty reasonable and the only
但是唯一点需要打破
point at which that breaks down is that
好吧，有几件事，其中之一是
um well it's a couple things one is if
如果程序员知道这个数据从未被共享
the programmer knew that the data was
他们可能会感觉烦恼
never shared they might be bummed that
因为他们得多付出锁的开销
they were paying the lock overhead for
他们清楚这没必要加锁
something they knew didn't need to be
所以这是个潜在的问题
locked so that's one potential problem
另一件事
the other is that if you if there's any
如果有任何内部数据结构依赖
inter data structure of dependencies so
比如我们有两个带有锁的数据结构
we have two data structures each with locks and
他们可能会互相使用
and they maybe use each other then
这可能会导致产生环和死锁
there's a risk of cycles and deadlocks
死锁可以被解决
right and the deadlocks can be solved
but the usual solutions to deadlocks
requires lifting the locks out of out of
the implementations up into the calling
code I will talk about that some point
but it's not a it's a good idea to hide
the locks but it's not always a good
idea all right okay so one problem you
run into with threads is these races and
generally you solve them with locks okay
or actually there's two big strategies
one is you figure out some locking
strategy for making access to the data
single thread one thread at a time or
you fix your code to not share data
if you can do that it's that's probably
better because it's less complex all
right so another issue that shows up
with leads threads is called
coordination when we're doing locking
the different threads involved probably
have no idea that the other ones exist
they just want to like be able to get
out the data without anybody else
interfering but there are also cases
where you need where you do
intentionally want different threads to
interact I want to wait for you
maybe you're producing some data you
know you're a different thread than me
you're you're producing data I'm gonna
wait until you've generated the data
before I read it right or you launch a
bunch of threads to say you crawl the
web and you want to wait for all those
fits to finish so there's times when we
intentionally want different to us to
interact with each other to wait for
each other
and that's usually called coordination
and there's a bunch of as you probably
know from having done the tutorial
there's a bunch of techniques in go for
doing this like channels
which are really about sending data from
one thread to another and breeding but
they did to be sent there's also other
stuff that more special purpose things
like there's a idea called condition
variables which is great if there's some
thread out there and you want to kick it
period you're not sure if the other
threads even waiting for you but if it
is waiting for you you just like to give
it a kick so it can well know that it
should continue whatever it's doing and
then there's wait group which is
particularly good for launching a a
known number of go routines and then
waiting for them Dolph to finish and a
final piece of damage that comes up with
threads deadlock the deadlock refers to
the general problem that you sometimes
run into where one thread
you know thread this thread is waiting
for thread two to produce something so
you know it's draw an arrow to say
thread one is waiting for thread two you
know for example thread one may be
waiting for thread two to release a lock
or to send something on the channel or
to you know decrement something in a
wait group however unfortunately maybe T
two is waiting for thread thread one to
do something and this is particularly
common in the case of locks its thread
one acquires lock a and thread to
acquire lock be so thread one is
acquired lock a throw two is required
lot B and then next thread one needs to
lock B also that is hold two locks which
sometimes shows up and it just so
happens that thread two needs to hold
block hey that's a deadlock all right at
least grab their first lock and then
proceed down to where they need their
second lock and now they're waiting for
each other forever right neither can
proceed neither then can release the
lock and usually just nothing happens so
if your program just kind of grinds to a
halt and doesn't seem to be doing
anything but didn't crash deadlock is
it's one thing to check
okay all right let's look at the web
crawler from the tutorial as an example
of some of this threading stuff I have a
couple of two solutions and different
styles are really three solutions in
different styles to allow us to talk a
bit about the details of some of this
thread programming so first of all you
all probably know web crawler its job is
you give it the URL of a page that it
starts at and you know many web pages
have links to other pages so what a web
crawler is trying to do is if that's the
first page extract all the URLs that
were mentioned that pages links you know
fetch the pages they point to look at
all those pages for the ules are all
those but all urls that they refer to
and keep on going until it's fetched all
the pages in the web let's just say and
then it should stop in addition the the
graph of pages and URLs is cyclic that
is if you're not careful
um you may end up following if you don't
remember oh I've already fetched this
web page already you may end up
following cycles forever and you know
your crawler will never finish so one of
the jobs of the crawler is to remember
the set of pages that is already crawled
or already even started a fetch for and
to not start a second fetch for any page
that it's already started fetching on
and you can think of that as sort of
imposing a tree structure finding a sort
of tree shaped subset of the cyclic
graph of actual web pages okay so we
want to avoid cycles we want to be able
to not fetch a page twice it also it
turns out that it just takes a long time
to fetch a web page but it's good
servers are slow and because the network
has a long speed of light latency and so
you definitely don't want to fetch pages
one at a time unless you want to crawl
to take many years so it pays enormous
lead to fetch many pages that same
I'm up to some limit right you want to
keep on increasing the number of pages
you fetch in parallel until the
throughput you're getting in pages per
second stops increasing that is running
increase the concurrency until you run
out of network capacity so we want to be
able to launch multiple fetches in
parallel and a final challenge which is
sometimes the hardest thing to solve is
to know when the crawl is finished
and once we've crawled all the pages we
want to stop and say we're done but we
actually need to write the code to
realize aha
we've crawled every single page and for
some solutions I've tried figuring out
when you're done has turned out to be
the hardest part all right so my first
crawler is this serial crawler here and
by the way this code is available on the
website under crawler go on the schedule
you won't look at it this wrist calls a
serial crawler it effectively performs a
depth-first search into the web graph
and there is sort of one moderately
interesting thing about it it keeps this
map called fetched which is basically
using as a set in order to remember
which pages it's crawled and that's like
the only interesting part of this you
give it a URL that at line 18 if it's
already fetched the URL it just returns
if it doesn't fetch the URL it first
remembers that it is now fetched it
actually gets fetches that page and
extracts the URLs that are in the page
with the fetcher and then iterates over
the URLs in that page and calls itself
for every one of those pages and it
passes to itself the way it it really
has just a one table there's only one
fetched map of course because you know
when I call recursive crawl and it
fetches a bunch of pages after it
returns I want to be where you know the
outer crawl instance needs to be aware
that certain pages are already fetched
so we depend very much on the fetched
map being passed between the functions
by reference instead of by copying so it
so under the hood what must really be
going on here is that go is passing a
pointer to the map object
to each of the calls of crawl so they
all share the pointer to the same object
and memory rather than copying rather
than copying than that any questions so
this code definitely does not solve the
problem that was posed right because it
doesn't launch parallel parallel fetches
now so clue we need to insert goroutines
somewhere in this code right to get
parallel fetches so let's suppose just
for chuckles dad we just start with the
most lazy thing because why so I'm gonna
just modify the code to run the
subsidiary crawls each in its own go
routine actually before I do that why
don't I run the code just to show you
what correct output looks like so hoping
this other window Emad run the crawler
it actually runs all three copies of the
crawler and they all find exactly the
same set of webpages so this is the
output that we're hoping to see five
lines five different web pages are are
fetched prints a line for each one so
let me now run the subsidiary crawls in
their own go routines and run that code
so what am I going to see the hope is to
fetch these webpages in parallel for
higher performance so okay so you're
voting for only seeing one URL and why
so why is that
yeah yes that's exactly right you know
after the after it's not gonna wait in
this loop at line 26 it's gonna zip
right through that loop I was gonna
fetch 1p when the ferry first webpage at
line 22 and then a loop it's gonna fly
off the Go routines and immediately
the scroll function is gonna return and
if it was called from main main what was
exit almost certainly before any of the
routines was able to do any work at all
so we'll probably just see the first web
page and I'm gonna do when I run it
you'll see here under serial that only
the one web page was found now in fact
since this program doesn't exit after
the serial crawler those Guru T's are
still running and they actually print
their output down here interleaved with
the next crawler example but
nevertheless the codes just adding a go
here absolutely doesn't work so let's
get rid of that okay so now I want to
show you a one style of concurrent
crawler and I'm presenting to one of
them written with shared data shared
objects and locks it's the first one and
another one written without shared data
but with passing information along
channels in order to coordinate the
different threads so this is the shared
data one or this is just one of many
ways of building a web crawler using
shared data so this code significantly
more complicated than a serial crawler
it creates a thread for each fetch it
does alright but the huge difference is
that it does with two things one it does
the bookkeeping required to notice when
all of the crawls have finished and it
handles the shared table of which URLs
have been crawled correctly so this code
still has this table of URLs and that's
this F dot fetched this F dot fetch
map at line 43 but this this table is
actually shared by all of the all of the
crawler threads and all the crawler
threads are making or executing inside
concurrent mutex and so we still have
this sort of tree up in current mutexes
that's exploring different parts of the
web graph but each one of them was
launched as a as his own go routine
instead of as a function call but
they're all sharing this table of state
this table of test URLs because if one
go routine fetches a URL we don't want
another Go routine to accidentally
fetch the same URL and as you can see
here line 42 and 45 I've surrounded them
by the new taxes that are required to to
prevent a race that would occur if I
didn't add them new Texas so the danger
here is that at line 43 a thread is
checking of URLs already been fetched so
two threads happen to be following the
same URL now two calls to concurrent
mutex end up looking at the same URL
maybe because that URL was mentioned in
two different web pages if we didn't
have the lock they'd both access the
math table to see if the threaded and
then already if the URL had been already
fetched and they both get false at line
43 they both set the URLs entering the
table to true at line 44 and at 47 they
will both see that I already was false
and then they both go on to patch the
web page so we need the lock there and
the way to think about it I think is
that we want lines 43 and 44 to be
atomic that is we don't want some other
thread to to get in and be using the
table between 43 and 44 we we want to
read the current content each thread
wants to read the current table contents
and update it without any other thread
interfering and so that's what the locks
are doing for us okay so so actually any
questions about the about the locking
strategy here
all right once we check the URLs entry
in the table alliant 51 it just crawls
it just fetches that page in the usual
way and then the other thing interesting
thing that's going on is the launching
of the threads yes so the question is
what's with the F dot no no the MU it is
okay so there's a structure to find out
line 36 that sort of collects together
all the different stuff that all the
different state that we need to run this
crawl and here it's only two objects but
you know it could be a lot more and
they're only grouped together for
convenience there's no other
significance to the fact there's no deep
significance the fact that mu and fetch
store it inside the same structure and
that F dot is just sort of the syntax
are getting out one of the elements in
the structure so I just happened to put
them you in the structure because it
allows me to group together all the
stuff related to a crawl but that
absolutely does not mean that go
associates the MU with that structure or
with the fetch map or anything it's just
a lock objects and just has a lock
function you can call and that's all
that's going on
so the question is how come in order to
pass something by reference I had to use
star here where it is when a in the
previous example when we were passing a
map we didn't have to use star that is
didn't have to pass a pointer I mean
that star notation you're seeing there
in mine 41 basically and he's saying
that we're passing a pointer to this
fetch state object and we want it to be
a pointer because we want there to be
one object in memory and all the
different go routines I want to use that
same object so they all need a pointer
to that same object so so we need to
find your own structure that's sort of
the syntax you use for passing a pointer
the reason why we didn't have to do it
with map is because although it's not
clear from the syntax a map is a pointer
it's just because it's built into the
language they don't make you put a star
there but what a map is is if you
declare a variable type map what that is
is a pointer to some data in the heap so
it was a pointer anyway and it's always
passed by reference do they you just
don't have to put the star and it does
it for you
so there's they're definitely map is
special you cannot define map in the
language it's it has to be built in
because there's some curious things
about it okay good okay so we fetch the
page now we want to fire off a crawl go
routine for each URL mentioned in the
page we just fetch so that's done in
line 56 on line 50 sisters loops over
the URLs that the fetch function
returned and for each one fires off a go
routine at line 58 and that lines that
func syntax in line 58 is a closure or a
sort of immediate function but that func
thing keyword is doing is to clearing a
function right there that we then call
so the way to read it maybe is
that if you can declare a function as a
piece of data as just func you know and
then you give the arguments and then you
give the body and that's a clears and so
this is an object now this is like it's
like when you type one when you have a
one or 23 or something you're declaring
a sort of constant object and this is
the way to define a constant function
and we do it here because we want to
launch a go routine that's gonna run
this function that we declared right
here and so we in order to make the go
routine we have to add a go in front to
say we want to go routine and then we
have to call the function because the go
syntax says the syntax of the go
keywords as you follow it by a function
name and arguments you want to pass that
function and so we're gonna pass some
arguments here and there's two reasons
we're doing this well really this one
reason we you know in some other
circumstance we could have just said go
concurrent mutex oh I concur mutex is
the name of the function we actually
want to call with this URL but we want
to do a few other things as well so we
define this little helper function that
first calls concurrent mutex for us with
the URL and then after them current
mutex is finished we do something
special in order to help us wait for all
the crawls to be done before the outer
function returns so that brings us to
the the wait group the wait group at
line 55 it's a just a data structure to
find by go to help with coordination and
the game with wait group is that
internally it has a counter and you call
wait group dot add like a line 57 to
increment the counter and we group done
to decrement it and then this wait
what this wait method called line 63
waits for the counter to get down to
zero so a wait group is a way to wait
for a specific number of things to
finish and it's useful in a bunch of
different situations here we're using it
to wait for the last go routine to
finish
because we add one to the wait group
for every go routine we create line 60
at the end of this function we've
declared decrement the counter in the
wait group and then line three waits
until all the decrements have finished
and so the reason why we declared this
little function was basically to be able
to both call concurrently text and call
done that's really why we needed that
function so the question is what if one
of the subroutines fails and doesn't
reach the done line that's a darn good
question there is you know if I forget
the exact range of errors that will
cause the go routine to fail without
causing the program to feel maybe
divides by zero I don't know where
dereference is a null pointer
not sure but there are certainly ways
for a function to fail and I have the go
routine die without having the program
die and that would be a problem for us
and so really the white right way to I'm
sure you had this in mind and asking the
question the right way to write this to
be sure that the done call is made no
matter why this go routine is finishing
would be to put a defer here which means
call done before the surrounding
function finishes and always call it no
matter why the surrounding function is
finished yes
and yes yeah so the question is how come
two users have done in different threads
aren't a race yeah so the answer must be
that internally dot a wait group has a
mutex or something like it that each of
Dunn's methods acquires before doing
anything else so that simultaneously
calls to a done to await groups methods
are trees we could to did a low class
yeah for certain leaf C++ and in C you
want to look at something called P
threads for C threads come in a library
they're not really part of the language
called P threads which they have these
are extremely traditional and ancient
primitives that all languages yeah
say it again you know not in this code
but you know you could imagine a use of
wait groups I mean wait groups just
count stuff and yeah yeah yeah wait
group doesn't really care what you're
pounding or why I mean you know this is
the most common way to see it use you're
wondering why you is passed as a
parameter to the function at 58 okay
yeah this is alright so the question is
okay so actually backing up a little bit
the rules for these for a function like
the one I'm defining on 58 is that if
the function body mentions a variable
that's declared in the outer function
but not shadowed then the the inner
functions use of that is the same
variable in the inner function as in the
outer function and so that's what's
happening with Fechter for example like
what is this variable here refer to what
does the Fechter variable refer to in
the inner function well it refers it's
the same variable as as the fetcher in
the outer function says just is that
variable and so when the inner function
refers to fetcher it just means it's
just referring the same variable as this
one here and the same with F f is it's
used here it's just is this variable so
you might think that we could get rid of
the this u argument that we're passing
and just have the inner function take no
arguments at all but just use the U that
was defined up on line 56 in the loop
and it'll be nice if we could do that
because save us some typing it turns out
not to work and the reason is that the
semantics of go of the for loop at line
56 is that the
for the updates the variable u so in
the first iteration of the for loop that
variable u contains some URL and when
you enter the second iteration before
the that variable this contents are
changed to be the second URL and that
means that the first go routine that we
launched that's just looking at the
outer if it we're looking at the outer
functions u variable the that first go
routine we launched would see a different
value in the u variable after the outer
function it updated it and sometimes
that's actually what you want so for
example for for F and then particular F
dot fetched we interaction absolutely
wants to see changes to that map but for
u we don't want to see changes the
first go routine we spawn should read
the first URL not the second URL so we
want that go routine to have a copy you
have its own private copy of the URL and
you know is we could have done it in
other ways we could have but the way
this code happens to do it to produce
the copy private to that inner function
is by passing the URLs in argument yes
yeah if we have passed the address of
u yeah then it uh it's actually I
don't know how strings work but it is
absolutely giving you your own private
copy of the variable you get your own
copy of the variable and it yeah
are you saying we don't need to play
this trick in the code we definitely
need to play this trick in the code and
what's going on is this it's so the
question is Oh strings are immutable
strings are immutable right yeah so how
kind of strings are immutable how can
the outer function change the string
there should be no problem the problem
is not that the string is changed the
problem is that the variable U is
changed so the when the inner function
mentions a variable that's defined in
the outer function it's referring to
that variable and the variables current
value so when you if you have a string
variable that has has a in it and then
you assign B to that string variable
you're not over writing the string
you're changing the variable to point to
a different string and and because the
for loop changes the U variable to point
to a different string you know that
change to you would be visible inside
the inner function and therefore the
inner function needs its own copy of the
variable
essentially make a copy of that so that
okay but that is what we're doing in
this code and that's that is why this
code works okay
the proposal or the broken code that
we're not using here I will show you the
broken code
this is just like a horrible detail but
it is unfortunately one that you'll run
into while doing the labs so you should
be at least where that there's a problem
and when you run into it maybe you can
try to figure out the details okay
that's a great question so so the
question is you know if you have an
inner function just a repeated if you
have an inner function that refers to a
variable in the surrounding function but
the surrounding function returns what is
the inner functions variable referring
to anymore since the outer function is
as returned and the answer is that go
notices go analyzes your inner functions
or these are called closures go analyzes
them the compiler analyze them says aha
oh this disclosure this inner function
is using a variable in the outer
function we're actually gonna and the
compiler will allocate heat memory to
hold the variable the you know the
current value of the variable and both
functions will refer to that that little
area heap that has the barrel so it
won't be allocated the variable won't be
on the stack as you might expect it's
moved to the heap if if the compiler
sees that it's using a closure and then
when the outer function returns the
object is still there in the heap the
inner function can still get at it and
then the garbage collector is
responsible for noticing that the last
function to refer to this little piece
of heat that's exited returned and to
free it only then okay okay
okay so wait group wait group is maybe
the more important thing here that the
technique that this code uses to wait
for all the all this level of crawls to
finished all its direct chill and the
finish is the wait group of course
there's many of these wait groups one
per call two concurrent mutex each call
that concurrent mutex just waits for its
own children to finish and then returns
okay so back to the lock actually
there's one more thing I want to talk
about with a lock and that is to explore
what would happen if we hadn't locked
right I'm claiming oh you know you don't
lock you're gonna get these races you're
gonna get incorrect execution whatever
let's give it a shot I'm gonna I'm gonna
comment out the locks and the question
is what happens if I run the code with
no locks what am I gonna see so we maght
see a url called twice or I fetch
twice yeah that's yeah that would be the
error you might expect alright so I'll
run it without locks and we're looking
at the concurrent map the one in the
middle this time it doesn't seem to have
fetched anything twice it's only five
run again gosh so far genius so maybe
we're wasting our time with those locks
yeah never seems to go wrong I've
actually never seem to go wrong so the
code is nevertheless wrong and someday
it will fail okay the problem is that
you know this is only a couple of
instructions here and so the chances of
these two threads which are maybe
hundreds of instructions happening to
stumble on this you know the same couple
of instructions at the same time is
quite low and indeed and and this is a
real bummer about buggy code with races
is that it usually works just fine but
it probably won't work when the customer
runs it on their computer
so it's actually bad news for us right
what do we you know it it can be in
complex programs quite difficult to
figure out if you have a race right and
you might you may have code that just
looks completely reasonable that is in
fact sort of unknown to you using shared
variables and the answer is you really
the only way to find races in practice
to be is you automated tools and luckily
go actually gives us this pretty good
race detector built-in to go and you
should use it so if you pass the - race
flag when you have to get your go
program and run this race detector which
well I'll run the race detector and
we'll see so it emits an error message
from us it's found a race and it
actually tells us exactly where the race
happened so there's a lot of junk in
this output but the really critical
thing is that the race detector realize
that we had read a variable that's what
this read is that was previously written
and there was no intervening release and
acquire of a lock that's what that's
what this means furthermore it tells us
the line number so it's told us that the
read was a line 43 and the write the
previous write was at line 44 and indeed
we look at the code and the read isn't
line 43 and the right is at line 44 so
that means that one thread did a write
at line 44 and then without any
intervening lock and another thread came
along and read that written data at line
43 that's basically what the race
detector is looking for the way it works
internally is it allocates sort of
shadow memory now lucky some you know it
uses a huge amount of memory and
basically for every one of your memory
locations the race detector is allocated
a little bit of memory itself in which
it keeps track of which threads recently
read or wrote every single memory
location and then when and it also to
keep tracking keeping track of when
threads acquiring release locks and do
other synchronization activities that it
knows forces but force threads to not
run
and if the race detector driver sees a
ha there was a memory location that was
written and then read with no
intervening market it'll raise an error
yes I believe it is not perfect yeah I
have to think about it what one
certainly one way it is not perfect is
that if you if you don't execute some
code the race detector doesn't know
anything about it so it's not analyzing
it's not doing static analysis the
racing sectors not looking at your
source and making decisions based on the
source it's sort of watching what
happened at on this particular run of
the program and so if this particular
run of the program didn't execute some
code that happens to read or write
shared data then the race detector will
never know and there could be erased
there so that's certainly something to
watch out for so you know if you're
serious about the race detector you need
to set up sort of testing apparatus that
tries to make sure all all the code is
executed but it's it's it's very good
and you just have to use it for your a
to 4 labs okay so this is race here and
of course the race didn't actually occur
what the race editor did not see was the
actual interleaving simultaneous
execution of some sensitive code right
it didn't see two threads literally
execute lines 43 and 44 at the same time
and as we know from having run the
things by hand that apparently doesn't
happen only with low probability all it
saw was at one point that was a right
and they made me much later there was a
read with no intervening lock and so
enact in that sense it can sort of
detect races that didn't actually happen
or didn't really cause bugs okay
okay one final question about this this
crawler how many threads does it create
yeah and how many concurrent threads
could there be yeah so a defect in this
crawler is that there's no obvious bound
on the number of simultaneous threads
that might create you know with the test
case which only has five URLs big
whoopee but if you're crawling a real
wheel web with you know I don't know are
there billions of URLs out there maybe
not we certainly don't want to be in a
position where the crawler might
accidentally create billions of threads
because you know thousands of threads
it's just fine billions of threads it's
not okay because each one sits on some
amount of memory so a you know there's
probably many defects in real life for
this crawler but one at the level we're
talking about is that it does create too
many threads and really ought to have a
way of saying well you can create 20
threads or 100 threads or a thousand
threads but no more so one way to do
that would be to pre create a pool a
fixed size pool of workers and have the
workers just iteratively look for
another URL to crawl crawl that URL
rather than creating a new thread for
each URL okay so next up I want to talk
about a another crawler that's
implemented and a significantly
different way using channels instead of
shared memory it's a member on the mutex
call or I just said there is this table
of URLs that are called that's shared
between all the threads and asked me
locked this version does not have such a
table does not share memory and does not
need to use locks okay so this one the
instead there's basically a master
thread that's his master function on a
decent 986 and it has a table but the
table is private to the master function
and what the master function is doing is
instead of sort of basically creating a
tree of functions that corresponds to
the exploration of the graph which the
previous crawler did this one fires off
one u one go routine per URL that it's
fetches and that but it's only the
master only the one master that's
creating these threads so we don't have
a tree of functions creating threads we
just have the one master okay so it
creates its own private map a line 88
this record what it's fetched and then
it also creates a channel just a single
channel that all of its worker threads
are going to talk to and the idea is
that it's gonna fire up a worker thread
and each worker thread that it fires up
when it finished such as fetching the
page will send exactly one item back to
the master on the channel and that item
will be a list of the URLs in the page
that that worker thread fetched so the
master sits in a loop we're in line
eighty nine is reading entries from the
channel and so we have to imagine that
it's started up some workers in advance
and now it's reading the information the
URL lists that those workers send back
and each time he gets a URL is sitting
on land eighty nine it then loops over
the URLs in that URL list from a single
page fetch align ninety and if the URL
hasn't already been fetched it fires off
a new worker at line 94 to fetch that
URL and if we look at the worker code
online starting line 77 basically calls
his fetcher and then sends a message on
the channel a line 80 or 82 saying
here's the URLs in the page they fetched
and notice that now that the maybe
interesting thing about this is that the
worker threads don't share any objects
there's no shared object between the
workers and the master so we don't have
to worry about locking we don't have to
worry about races instead this is a
example of sort of communicating
information instead of getting at it
through shared memory yes
yeah yeah so the observation is that the
code appears but the workers are the
observation is the workers are modifying
ch while the Masters reading it and
that's not the way the go authors would
like you to think about this the way
they want you to think about this is
that CH is a channel and the channel has
send and receive operations and the
workers are sending on the channel while
the master receives on the channel and
that's perfectly legal the channel is
happy I mean what that really means is
that the internal implementation of
channel has a mutex in it and the
channel operations are careful to take
out the mutex when they're messing with
the channels internal data to ensure
that it doesn't actually have any
reasons in it but yeah channels are sort
of protected against concurrency and
you're allowed to use them concurrently
from different threads yes
over the channel receive yes
we don't need to close the channel I
mean okay the the break statement is
about when the crawl has completely
finished and we fetched every single URL
right because hey what's going on is the
master is keeping I mean this n value is
private value and a master every time it
fires off a worker at increments the end
though every worker it starts since
exactly one item on the channel and so
every time the master reads an item off
the channel it knows that one of his
workers is finished and when the number
of outstanding workers goes to zero then
we're done and we don't once the number
the only reference to the channel is
from the master or from oh really from
the code that calls the master and so
the garbage collector will very soon see
that the channel has no references to it
and will free the channel so in this
case sometimes you need to close
channels but actually I rarely have to
close channels
he said again
so the question is alright so you can
see at line 106 before calling master
concurrent channel sort of fires up one
shoves one URL into the channel and it's
to sort of get the whole thing started
because the code for master was written
you know the master goes right into
reading from the channel line 89 so
there better be something in the channel
otherwise line 89 would block forever so
if it weren't for that little code at
line 107 the for loop at 89 would block
reading from the channel forever and
this code wouldn't work well yeah so the
observation is gosh you know wouldn't it
be nice to be able to write code that
would be able to notice if there's
nothing waiting on the channel and you
can if you look up the Select statement
it's much more complicated than this but
there is the Select statement which
allows you to proceed to not block if
something if there's nothing waiting on
the channel
because the worker aren't finish okay sorry
to the first question is there I think
what you're really worried about is
whether we're actually able to launch
parallel so the very first fetch won't be
in parallel because there's an exit
owner the for-loop waits in at line 89
that's not okay that for loop at line 89
is does not just loop over the current
contents of the channel and then quit
that is the for loop at 89 is going to
read it may never exit but it's gonna
read it's just going to keep waiting
until something shows up in the channel
so if you don't hit the break at line 99
the for loop own exit yeah alright I'm
afraid we're out of time we'll continue
this actually we have a presentation
scheduled by the TAS which I'll talk
more about go